Guide to the Walter Gordon Merritt Collection MS 014
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Walter Gordon Merritt Collection
1902-1967, (Bulk 1920-1946)
1920-1946
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Merritt, Walter Gordon.
MS 014
124
0.5 Linear Feet, 1 box
In 1902 Walter Gordon Merritt entered the national labor scene in the Danbury hatters strike as counsel for the hat companies. This collection contains many of Walter Gordon Merritt's published articles and pamphlets regarding labor and management relations.
Provenance
This collection consists of a gift from Alison Roth and a gift from Mrs. W.G. Merritt in 1977.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
In 1902 Walter Gordon Merritt entered the national labor scene in the Danbury hatters' strike as counsel for the hat companies. This strike stands as a landmark in the labor history because it led to the Supreme Court decision that placed unions and their members under the provisions of the Sherman Antitrust Act. For many years after the strike, Merritt worked continuously on the labor scene handling labor law as a partner in the firm of McLanahan, Merritt, and Ingraham. Mr. Merritt's views and evolution of his thinking have been of interest to labor and management alike.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains many of Walter Gordon Merritt's published articles and pamphlets regarding labor and management relations. In addition, there are copies of letters Merritt received commenting on an article he wrote in the February 1957 issue of the American Bar Association Journal. Correspondents include: Victor W. Knauth, A.Willis Robertson, Mrs. William F. Bevan, Henry H. Curran, Paul D. Wilbur, Arthur Ballantine, Arthur J. Goldberg, Charles P. Collins, Floyd M. Kocher, Paul L. Poirot, Max Powell, L. S. Goldberg, Howell Spear, Harold E. Craw, Brice P. Disque, Claude McColloch, Carroll E. French, Richard L. Nahley, John H. Roos, and Angelo Patri.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
Inventory
Labor unions.; New Fairfield (Conn.); Danbury (Conn.); Strikes and lockouts.; Open and closed shops; Fliers (printed matter); Publications.; Correspondence.; Speeches.; Labor -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Boycotts.; Industrial relations-United States.; Merritt, Walter Gordon.; Schwellenbach, Lewis B.; League for Industrial Rights.
- Inventory, 39257
  - Address of Walter Gordon Merritt before the National Association of Building Owners and Managers. June 18, 1946., 39280 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - America's Town Meeting of the Air. How Should the Government Deal with the Labor Problem? Broadcast from The Town Hall, New York overthe NBC Blue Network. Walter Gordon Merritt and Lewis B. Schwellenbach., 1937; 39279 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Argument of Walter Gordon Merritt Proposing Amendments to Wagner Industrial Disputes Act., undated; 39278 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1967; 39277 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Factory Solidarity or Class Solidarity?, undated; 39276 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Four C's of Industry. March 1923., 39275 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - History of the League for Industrial Rights., 1925; 39274 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Labor, Law, and Order, A Composite., 1915; 39273 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Labor Policies of the 30's Call for Changes in the 40's. An address byWalter Gordon Merritt. February 1946. (2 copies), 1942; 39272 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Labor Unions and The Law., undated; 39271 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Memorandum of Realty Advisory Board in Opposition to Closed Shop. Before the National War Labor Board. In the Matter of Realty AdvisoryBoard on Labor Relations, Inc. and Building Service EmployeesInternational Union, Local 32-F, A.F. of L. Case no. 141., undated; 39270 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Neglected Side of Trade-Unionism. The Boycott., 1902; 39269 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Articles, 1916-1966; 39268 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Open Shop; A Debate. Andrew Furuseth, President of the International Seamen's Union versus Walter Gordon Merritt, Counsel of the League forIndustrial Rights. March 13, 1921., 39267 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Open Shop and Industrial Liberty. June 1922., 39266 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Organized Labor and Democracy, undated; 39265 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Our Unbalanced Labor Policy., 1902-1967; 39264 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Regulation of Labor Unions. A Discussion of Fundamental Principles As Suggested by a Regulatory Bill Introduced in the Legislature of the State of New York in March 1937., 39263 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Speeches, 1919-1955; 39262 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The Struggle for Industrial Liberty., 1922; 39261 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Town Meeting. The Open or Closed Shop for War Industries? March 23, 1942., 39260 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Two Federal Legislatures?, 1944; 39259 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cassette tape (oral interview), April 1964, 39258 (Box 1, Folder *)